# Zhiyuan Ge Ph.D.

Assistant professor at College of Geosciences, China University of Petroleum (Beijing), China

Phone: +86 15901127735 Email: gezhiyuan@cup.edu.cn

I am an assistant professor at College of Geosciences, China University of Petroleum (Beijing). My research mainly focuses on the tectono-stratigraphic evolution of sedimentary basins, particularly the interaction between salt-controlled structures and deep-water sedimentation. I have worked closely with industry in multiple research projects in the last couple of years. Currently I am involved in a research project between University of Bergen and German Research Centre for Geosciences (GFZ) focusing on salt tectonics in passive margins. I have published over 10 peer-reviewed articles in international geoscience journals.

Website: <a href="https://geogezhiyuan.netlify.app/">https://geogezhiyuan.netlify.app/</a>

## 1. Education background and research experiences

# 1A. Education background

2011.10 - 2015.10	PhD	Department of Earth Science, University of Bergen, Norway
2009.09 - 2010.09	Master	Department of Earth Sciences, Royal Holloway, Uni. of London, UK
2005.09 - 2009.06	Bachelor	Department of Earth Sciences, Zhejiang University, China

# 1B. Research experiences

2016.07 – present	Postdoc researcher, PhD co-supervisor	University of Bergen, Norway
2013.09 - 2014.06	Teaching assistant	University of Bergen, Norway
2010.10 - 2011.10	Research assistant	Royal Holloway, University of London, UK

#### 1C. Research visit

2018.06 – 2018.09, 2019.07	German Research Centre for Geosciences (GFZ), Germany
2008.08	Seismology Bureau of Zhejiang Province, China

# 2. Research project

#### 2A. Project leader (PI)

- 1. EON Foundation and EPOS (European Plate Observing System) sponsored project, 'Minibasin evolution in passive margin salt basins', 2018;
- 2. University of Bergen, SPIRE project, 2017–2018;

#### 2B. Project investigator

- 1. Statoil (now Equinor) sponsored project, 'Turbidites, Topography and Tectonics (T<sup>3</sup>): understanding the response of turbidity currents to structurally controlled seafloor topography', 2016 to present.
- 2. Total Norge AS sponsored project, 'Late Jurassic tectono-stratigraphic development of the Norwegian Central Graben and the influence of normal faulting on turbidite sedimentation', 2011–2015
- 3. PetroBras sponsored project, 'Kinematics and Mechanics of Salt-related Fold & Fault Structures

### 3. Publication

- 1. Howlett, D.\*, Gawthorpe, R., Ge, Z., Rotevatn, A., & Jackson, C. A-L, (2020), Turbidites, Topography and Tectonics: Evolution of submarine channel-lobe systems in the salt-influenced Kwanza Basin, offshore Angola. *Basin Research* (under review)
- 2. **Ge, Z.\***, Gawthorpe, R., Zijerveld, L., & Oluboyo, A. P., (2020), Controls on variations of geometry and stratigraphy in salt minibasins: Lower Congo Basin, Angola Margin. *Basin Research*
- 3. **Ge, Z.\***, Warsitzka, M., Rosenau, M., & Gawthorpe, R., (2019), Progressive margin tilting controls thin-skinned deformation in salt-bearing basins. *Geology*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1130/G46485.1
- 4. **Ge, Z.\***, Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., Zijerveld, L., Jackson, C. A.-L., & Oluboyo, A. P., (2019), Minibasin depocentre migration during diachronous salt welding, offshore Angola. *Basin Research*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1111/bre.12404
- 5. **Ge, Z.\***, Rosenau, M., Warsitzka, M., & Gawthorpe, R., (2019), Overprinting translational domains in passive margin salt basins: Insights from analogue modelling. *Solid Earth*. doi: doi.org/10.5194/se-10-1283-2019
- 6. Howlett, D. M.\*, **Ge, Z.,** Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Jackson, C. A.-L., (2019) Response of unconfined turbidity current to deep-water thrust fold-belt topography: orthogonal incidence on solitary and segmented folds. *Sedimentology*. doi: 10.1111/sed.12602
- 7. **Ge, Z.\***, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Ernst, H., (2018) Response of unconfined turbidity current to relay-ramp topography: insights from process-based numerical modelling. *Basin Research*, doi:10.1111/bre.12255
- 8. **Ge, Z.\***, Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Thomas, M., (2017) Impact of normal faulting and pre-rift salt tectonics on the structural style of salt-influenced rifts: the Late Jurassic Norwegian Central Graben, North Sea. *Basin Research*, doi:10.1111/bre.12219
- 9. **Ge, Z.\*,** Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., & Ernst, H., (2017) Response of unconfined turbidity current to normal-fault topography. *Sedimentology*, 64: 932–959. doi:10.1111/sed.12333
- 10. Adam, J.\*, **Ge, Z.,** & Sanchez, M. (2012). Salt-structural styles and kinematic evolution of the Jequitinhonha deepwater fold belt, central Brazil passive margin. *Marine and Petroleum Geology*, 37(1), 101-120.
- 11. Adam, J.\*, **Ge, Z.,** & Sanchez, M. (2012). Post-rift salt tectonic evolution and key control factors of the Jequitinhonha deepwater fold belt, central Brazil passive margin: Insights from scaled physical experiments. *Marine and Petroleum Geology*, 37(1), 70-100.

### 4. Conferences

- 1. **Ge, Z.**, Warsitzka, M., Rosenau, M. & Gawthorpe, R.L. The Impact of Instant Versus Progressive Margin Tilting Upon Passive Margin Salt Basins. AAPG GTW EuroAsian Mature Salt Basins, Krakow, April 2019.
- 2. **Ge, Z.,** Warsitzka, M., Rotevatn, A., Gawthorpe, R.L., Zijerveld, L. & T. Wrona. Extension initiation and localization on minibasin formation in passive margin salt basins. TSG, Bergen, Jan 2019.
- 3. **Ge, Z.**, Rosenau, M., Warsitzka, M. & Gawthorpe, R.L. Kinematic domain partitioning in passive margin salt basins: the myth of translational domain. GeoMod2018, Barcelona, Oct. 2018.
- 4. Howlett, D. M., **Ge, Z.**, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R.L., Rotevatn, A., Response of Unconfined Turbidity Currents to Complex Bathymetry in Deepwater Fold and Thrust Belts. AAPG 2018 ACE, Salt Lack City, May 2018.
- 5. **Ge, Z.**, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R.L., Rotevatn, A., Basani, R. & Hansen, E.W.M. The impact of fault topography on turbidity currents descending from the slope to the floor of an early-stage deep-water rift basin: insights from CFD numerical simulations. IAS 2013. Manchester, Sep. 2013.
- 6. **Ge, Z**., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Wonham, J. Variations in Depocentre Style under Mid-Late Jurassic Salt-Influenced Rifting: Norwegian Central Graben, North Sea. AAPG 2013 ACE, Pittsburgh, May 2013.